<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An humble addresse to the right honourable Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament in vindication of kingly power and government against the damnable positions of Jesuits and phanatiques desiring they would be pleased to call in the king without dishonourable conditions according to his just right / written by the author of a letter to a member.</title>
            <author>Author of A letter to a member.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44969</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3391</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31130</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11780305</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11780305</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49016</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44969)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49016)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1485:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An humble addresse to the right honourable Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament in vindication of kingly power and government against the damnable positions of Jesuits and phanatiques desiring they would be pleased to call in the king without dishonourable conditions according to his just right / written by the author of a letter to a member.</title>
                  <author>Author of A letter to a member.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Peter Lillicrap for Henry Marsh ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verso has royal arms.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monarchy --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:49016:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49016:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An Humble ADDRESSE To the Right Honourable LORDS &amp; COMMONS Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT, In vindication of KINGLY POWER AND GOVERNMENT Againſt the Damnable Poſitions of Jeſuits and Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, deſiring they would be pleaſed to call in the King without diſhonourable conditions according to his Juſt Right.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by the Author of a Letter to a Member.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Rom. <hi>Chap.</hi> 13. <hi>ver.</hi> 1.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher Powers, for there is no Power but of God, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Peter Lillicrap,</hi> for <hi>Henry Marſh,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the Princes Arms in <hi>Chancery-lane.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="address">
            <pb facs="tcp:49016:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49016:2"/>
            <head>An Humble ADDRESSE To the Right honourable LORDS and COMMONS Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT, <hi>In vindication of Kingly Power and Government againſt the damnable Poſitions of Jeſuites and Phanatiques, deſiring they would be pleaſed to call in the King without diſhonourable conditions according to his juſt rights.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Othing in this world can preſent this ſad nation with ſo pleaſant a ſight as your Honourable Seſſion in Parliament, which giveth a rapture of joy to all Loyal and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hearts, tranſporting them with the high contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of the inexhauſtible Treaſure of Divine mercy, that God out of the wiſe conduct of his ever to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red providence (after our great and various Tragick ſcenes of Governours and Governments acted by the politick Jeſuits, the great State-mongers, in their ſecret influence on the Counſels of this nation) ſhould diſpoſe your much prayed for Convention, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of our hearts, and deſire of our ſouls, as the onely expedient left us under God to reedifie the ruined Church, and to repair the ſad breaches of the decaied State.</p>
            <p>You are the expected Center, in which the ſeveral lines of different
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49016:3"/>intereſts meet, that after their diverſe unhappy motions in you (their proper place) they may receive reſt and perfection; you are that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigne Conſtellation in the ſphere of Government, by whoſe propicious influence, all things in our lower orbe receive the more refined producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their better being, in the conception, birth and maturity of our bleſſed reſtauration.</p>
            <p>Me thinketh theſe many years in the ſad winter of our afflicted Clymate, all things ſeem to have been void of fire and ſpirit, but your pre ence like a warm ſpring reviveth our withered expectations, and inliveneth our dull bodies with a new ſoul, full of like opperations; and after the long Lent of our moſt low condition, we are bleſſed with an Eaſter of your meeting, which after the death of our hopes, giveth a reſurrection of our happines; which offereth us an argument for ever to magnifie Gods unſpeakable goodneſs, and an opportunity to congratulate the proſperous eſtate of the Kingdom in you, our moſt faithfull Truſtees, and to ſpeak our thanks, that you are pleaſed to take upon you the trouble to redreſs our intolerable grievances, and to redeem the diſtreſſed Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, long groaning under many heavy preſſures from high ſlavery and eminent ruine.</p>
            <p>The beſt way to prevent it is to find out the firſt original, on which as a prime cauſe the great complication of our miſeries dependeth, and truly without any curious diſquiſition you may perceive it to flow from diſobedience to that Authoty, which God hath ſet over us, and the grand Error in principles hath proved ſo fruitful, that it hath had many branches ſpringing out of it according to the Phyloſophers received maxime in his Phyſicks, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one Capital Error begetteth a thouſand.</p>
            <p>It is that unhappy diſpute (which the two Houſes had with the King, firſt embroiled the Nation in a Civil war, and then involved it in a Labrinth of miſeries! when blood is once drawn, it is very diſſicult to ſtench the flux of it; the ſurviving always being acted with a bitter animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to revenge the quarrell of their murdred friends, each party being ambitious to gain the glory of a conqueſt and ſoverainty over others, are ſo much biaſſed with their own intereſt of an earthly enjoyment of them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elves, as they aim to be Maſters of other mens eſtates and fortunes, which giveth a high diſturbance to the conquered party, who will be always unwilling to ſit down with loſs of liberty and livelyhood.</p>
            <p>Pray be pleaſed to uſe the utmoſt of your induſtry in your prudent Counſels, to make ſuch a proviſion for the future to take away all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and lay aſide ſuch diſputes, which will inevitably produce a new
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49016:3"/>War, which to hinder, nothing is ſo rational, as to fix the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdom upon the antient baſis, which is the means to ſatisfie all honeſt intereſts, and as for the other it is as fond as diſingenious to gratifie them, they being ſo inconſiderable cannot pretend to merit any bodies eſteem.</p>
            <p>I know it is your Chriſtian intention, and the peoples great advantage to make a firm and laſting peace, which will be crowned with ſo good a product, as the Kingdoms flouriſhing eſtate, and the con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation of your bleſſed memories to poſterity. Nothing can be more honourable to the Nation, and ſuitable to the genius of the people, then the antient eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Government, which ſpeaketh great Attributes of glory and wiſdom to our forefathers, who have founded ſuch an admirable fabrick of Polity among us, that after ages have rendred themſelves no leſs miſerable, then contemptible in the alteration of it.</p>
            <p>The late unfortunate revolutions will eaſily convince the refractory oppoſers, that Monarchy is the beſt modell of all Polities whatſoever, holding a correſpondence in ſome manner with Gods Government, all inferiour Creatures (as his ſubjects) by a natural impreſs ſerving each other in an admirable order, Naturals ſerving the Plants, and Plants the Animals, and Animals the Rationals, and at laſt Heaven and Earth and all the ſeveral orders of Entities out of a principle of Nature, reaſon or religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, pay a tribute of obedience and devotion to God their ſupreme om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent Monarch.</p>
            <p>This Loyalty of the Creature is preſidentary to men indued with a more ſublime principle of Reaſon, and united in a common ſociety, are oblieged to be ſubſervient to each other in their ſuperiour or inferiour degrees of ſubjection, or command, to promote the common wellfare, and moſt conſcientiouſly to perform all ſervice and duty to the King by his lawful inheritance, and Gods divine inſtitution, their ſupreme go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor.</p>
            <p>And as more naturals that Elements ought of a univerſal dictate move upwards and downwards, contrary to their particular inclinations, in ſilling up a vacuum, to ſerve the common good of the univerſe, and to keep inviolable the law of the Creator, I wiſh none placed in a ſphere above them, being courted by their example, would be ſo farre elevated above their private concerns, and endeavour (though contrary to their ſelf advantages) by all means poſſible to advance the publike good in their regular ſubordination to the King, the ſupreme Governour of the Nation, And therefore I deſire you would nighly di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>countenance that baſe Jeſuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call principle (a fundamental Error in Politicks, the ſowers of all Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49016:4"/>and Annarchy) that Kings and all in Authority have their power from the People, which is as truly falſe in it ſelf as fatal to this Nation.</p>
            <p>For though the People do nominate Kings <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in elective kingdoms, or conſent to them in Hereditary (as ours is, and the Crown ought to be tranſmitted to our moſt gracious Soveraign from a long ſeries of his nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous and royal progenitors) yet their nomination, or conſent is either by way of fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m or order, to declare an approvement of, or ſubmiſſion to the King as the ſupreme Power of the kingdom: which is derived by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine inſtitution from God himſelf (the ſole moſt obſolute eternal Monarch and fountain of all lawfull Power) it being no more in the People to give Power to Kings, then in their own Power to give themſelves being.</p>
            <p>All Power being Authoritative originally or radically in God, as the firſt founder, in the King Repreſentative <hi>&amp; per modum ſubjecti,</hi> as a ſubject capable of the juſt managery of it: and in the People materially, <hi>&amp; per modum patientis,</hi> in the nomination of the Perſon (not the conſtitution of Power) in their choiſe in Elective kingdoms, and by their conſent do not give a Power, be an attribute of obedience in their due ſubſcription to it in hereditary.</p>
            <p>We have Gods <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for it <hi>per me Regis regnant,</hi> by me Kings reign. By me <hi>Conſtitutive &amp; efficienter, per modum Authoris,</hi> as the ſupreme Agent, and Kings do reign <hi>Miniſterialiter per modum Dei locum tenentium,</hi> as Gods Vicegerents, their Power being a Ray of Divinity, by whoſe benigne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, mankinde (the flower of the univerſe, watered in ſhowers of graces from above, and ſtreams of Juſtice below) receiveth its bud and perfection under his propitious conduct in a happy planting and orderly maturing all things in this inferiour world.</p>
            <p>And therefore Kings and all in Authority are not of the Peoples but of Gods chriſtionizing, and that after his own Name, <hi>I ſaid ye are Gods:</hi> whereupon for his ſake, and by virtue of his Commiſſion (as his Deputies) the People are liable to pay a juſt tribute of obedience to them.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe that Kings and thoſe who are in Authority ſhall (as the Phanaticks of this age object) neglect the great end of Government, and improve all opportunities and advantages of their Power and Grandeur unto their own perſonal and family intereſt, eſpecially when they ſhall wilfully and againſt univerſal reaſon and the apparent danger of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſafety, then ſay they, they determine their Authority, and having in ſuch caſes quitted their care and reſpects to the Peoples protection, they likewiſe quite the People from their Allegeance and obedience.</p>
            <p>To this damnable and Jeſuitical Poſition, I thus reply. It is rare to find Kings (they and their People being Correlatives) to have ſo much cruelty
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49016:5"/>for themſelves, as in bauiſhing the univerſal Dictates of Reaſon, in the common ruine of their kingdoms, theirs and the Peoples being one joynt intereſt, and their greateſt concern (next the glory of God) is a mutual oppoſition of enemies, and a joynt concurrence in vigorous endeavours for the ſupport and promotion of each others happineſs.</p>
            <p>But grant that Kings ſhould ſo far degenerate as to cancel all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations to God and nature, in order to Liberty and Propriety of their People; it is no more then is clearly deſcribed in the ſacred Oracles, where <hi>Samuel</hi> ſtateth the abſolute Prerogative of a King, 1 <hi>Sam. Chap.</hi> 8. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. to the 17. <hi>And he ſaid, this ſhall be the manner of the King that ſhall reign over you, he will take your ſons, and appoint them for himſelf, for his Chariots.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let them take their much admired <hi>Calvins</hi> authentick Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe on the text (out of his care done to truth rather then Kings) in the latter end of the 26 Paragraph, <hi>De publica Adminiſtratione: Ac ſi dixiſſet Samuel, eo ſe proripiet licentiae Regum libido, quam cohibere ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum non erit, quibus hoc reſtabit unum, juſſa excipere, ac dicto audientes eſſe.</hi> To ſuch a height of Tyranny ſhall the will of Kings break forth, which to reſtrain is not your duty, in you this onely remaineth, to hearken to his words, and obey his commands, with which you are in humble ſubmiſſion to comply, and not in a rebellious reſiſtance to diſpute.</p>
            <p>And to that effect is that moſt ſignal place of Scripture, <hi>Jer. chap.</hi> 27. <hi>ver.</hi> 6. and 8. <hi>And now have I given all thoſe lands into the hands of Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar the King of Babylon my ſervant, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who this <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> was is ſufficiently known, who had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the holy City, and had by his abſolute power in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded other Territories, yet God ſtyleth him <hi>Nebnchadnezzar my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant</hi> (though a great Tyrant and Uſurper) by virtue of his unqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable Commiſſion, which none but God himſelf could take from him. And once more be pleaſed to take <hi>Calvins</hi> Comment upon the recited Text; <hi>Videmus quanta obedientia Dominus tetrum illum ferocem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Tyrannum coli voluerit, non alia ratione niſi quia Regnum obtinebat;</hi> You ſee (ſaith he) with what obedience the Lord would have that cruel Tyrant obſerved, upon no other account, but as he was by himſelf inveſted with the Royal Throne. And <hi>Calvin</hi> further ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth in the ſame Paragraph, <hi>Eodem decreto conſtitui etiam nequiſſimos Reges quo Regum authoritas ſtatuitur; nunquam in animum nobis ſeditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae illae cogitationes venient, tractandum eſſe pro meritis Regem; nec aequum
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49016:6"/>eſſe ut ſubditos ei non praeſtemus, qui viciſſim Regem nobis ſe non praeſtat;</hi> By the ſame Commiſſion are wicked Kings conſtituted, by which the Authority of Kings in general is enacted; and we muſt never enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain within our minds ſuch Rebellious thoughts, how that the King is to be treated according to his demerits, neither is it fit we ſhould with draw our obedience as ſubjects, though he doth not expreſs his gracious clemency and Moderation as a King.</p>
            <p>Therefore theſe Phanatick objections of this latter age ſince 1642 are very unjuſtifiable, that ſervice and obedience is to be wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted onely to the juſt commands of ſuperiors; this is that diſloyal principle which hath introduced ſo much Barbariſme and confuſion among us, which hath an ill aſpect upon our Oeconomicks as well as Politicks, and hath gained an opinion with wives, children and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, that no ſervice is to be given by the one to their Maſters, nor duty by the other to their Parents, nor obedience by the third to their Husbands, if Maſters, Parents, or Husbands do (as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) impoſe their ſevere commands upon them, and if they act any thing contrary to their fancy, they deem they may juſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe all obligations whatſoever due by Religion, Law and the right of Nature to their ſeveral Relations.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe that Kings and all in Authority ſhall neglect the great ends of Government, and improve all opportunities and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages to their own perſonal intereſt, to the apparent danger of of common ſafety (ſay the Phanaticks) they determine their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and having quitted their care of the Peoples protection they quit the People from their Allegiance and Obedience.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, That Kings though moſt abſolute Tyrants can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be juſtly depoſed by the People; I confeſs the end of all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is the common good in a due adminiſtration of Juſtice, to the promotion of which all their royal endeavours, as ſo many lines ought to concenter themſelves (as in a point) in the publick ſafety of their ſubjects.</p>
            <p>And although Kings do not perform their duty, in governing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law, yet their Authority doth not determine, it being ſupreme is lyable to give an account onely to God, who onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termineth both the Power and Perſon.</p>
            <p>And although the people do by Election or Conſent confer a truſt on Kings and Governors, which is abſolute, no Governour being ſo weak as to take it on the condition of his good behaviour, <hi>&amp; durante Populi beneplacito,</hi> the will of the people being as mutable as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49016:6"/>fond, and having not alwaies Reaſon for its Conduct, and ſolid principles for its Baſis, under pretence of ill managery, will ſpeak a determination to the lawful power of a ſupreme Governour, and the beſt modelled Government of a Nation.</p>
            <p>It is very reaſonable to grant that the people do give a very high truſt to Kings and thoſe in Authority, which is ſealed to them by Gods power, <hi>Be ſubject to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake,</hi> from whom Kings receive the <hi>Patent</hi> of their Authority, which no body under any gloſs how fair ſoever can cancel, he being in no capacity to forfeit that power to man, which he hath immediately derived from God alone, I mean the ſword of Juſtice; it being not in the power of the people originally to kill one another without a Magiſtrate, they being endued with an equality in nature, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not exerciſe this ſoveraignty over each other. And if the King could forfeit his truſt by not diſcharging it according to the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Donors, and the Laws to which he hath obliged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that the people cannot reſume that truſt, when it hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the approbation and confirmation of Gods power, which the people cannot aſſume to themſelves, without the moſt impious ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogating one of the ſupreme Attributes of God to themſelves.</p>
            <p>But then it will be replyed that the people are in a ſad condition, having no ſence againſt the arbitrary power of Kings: to which I briefly anſwer, they have for their refuge Tears and Prayers, the Arms of the Church in their greateſt ſtraits and perplexities, and God, in whoſe hands the hearts of Kings are to turn them as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth according to his holy wiſdom; and for my part, I ſhall ever deem it better to live under the Tyranny of Kings then under the Anarchy of the people.</p>
            <p>I deſire you would be pleaſed to make a deep inſpection into thoſe two erroneous principles ſo much cried up by the <hi>Phanaticks,</hi> that <hi>ſalus populi eſt ſuprema lex,</hi> and <hi>Rex eſt ſingulis major, &amp; univerſis minor;</hi> which they conceive are moſt abſolute rules to walk by, and a firm baſis to ſecure their curſed actions from the titles of rebellion, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, ſacriledge, murder, oppreſſion, &amp;c. To the firſt, that the ſafety of the people is the ſupreme law, I thus anſwer; the ſafety of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in ſtrict ſpeech is not a law, but an end of it, the law being made for the juſt conſervation of the peoples ſafety; but grant it in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon language to be a law, and then ſure none is ſo void of ſenſe and reaſon, if an end may be called a law, but to give to the ultimate end the attribute of ſupremacy, and then <hi>Gloria Deieſt ſuprema lex,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:49016:7"/>and indeed his word is a law, and it is his glory to maintain it. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher powers;</hi> and God ſo far condeſcendeth as to give a reaſon of it, <hi>for the Powers that are are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the debate will be, who is ſupreme, the King or the people; I confeſs the people <hi>de facto</hi> have of late made themſelves ſo, but I hope they have not the boldneſs <hi>de jure</hi> to think ſo, the Legiſlative power being ultimately in the King, by whoſe Royal conſent the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults of the two Houſes (who are called and diſſolved by his power) receive the ſignature of Laws; the houſe of Commons being Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned by him <hi>ad inquireddum,</hi> and the houſe of Lords <hi>ad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulendum,</hi> and in him their legal head is the ſupreme power <hi>ad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminandum de ordine negotiis regni,</hi> it is his right with the advice of Parliaments his great Council to determine what is the ſafety, peace and the juſt Rights of the nation, and not in the people, who are not a head of law, but the body of the kingdom to be governed by it.</p>
            <p>And if the People ſhould deem in their private ſenſe (which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſo diſcerning and impartial as the publick judgement of thoſe that are placed on the hill of government, who ſee much more then they that kneel in the valley of ſubjection) that the known fundamental Laws inſtituted by them (who are Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters) are diametrically oppoſite to the juſt intereſt of a nation, yet if they cannot (it being repugnant to their conſcience to give an active obſervance to thoſe laws made, as they apprehend, againſt the ſafety of the people) yet they are oblieged to give a paſſive obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Governours (who as they are ordained, if good, are to give him onely an account of their actions) in an humble ſubmiſſion to whatſoever puniſhments ſhall be impoſed by them.</p>
            <p>And here the people are readily to write after our bleſſed Saviours excellent copy, who ſubmitted to an unjuſt power in the loſs of his life, contrary to all law, rather then diſpute his own ordinance; and ſo it is better for them in Chriſtian patience to die Martyrs, then by an illegal reſiſtance to be rebells.</p>
            <p>To that their maxime (being a main foundation upon which the Phanaticks have at firſt built, and ſtill endeavour to ſupport that moſt unhandſome ſuperſtructure of Rebellion, Sacriledge, Perjury, and in a word, their violation of all humane and divine Laws) that <hi>Rex eſt ſingulis major, &amp; univerſis minor,</hi> the King is greater then any ſingle perſon, and leſſer then the community of the people; to which I reply, that the body of the people cannot pretend to be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49016:7"/>or rival with him, except his two Houſes of Parliament, who have no being, unleſs they receive birth by his ſummons, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulere de arduis negotiis regni,</hi> and ſo they may be juſtly ſtyled his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours to adviſe, and not his ſuperiours to command.</p>
            <p>The Legiſlative power (which to vindicate he is armed with the <hi>Militia</hi> of the Nation) being principally ſeated in him, that thoſe wholeſome laws which derive their rough draught, and firſt delinea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of parts from the two Houſes, and afterward their life and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity from the ſignature of his Excellent Majeſties Royal conſent.</p>
            <p>Again, the King may challenge a preeminence over the whole body of the people, in reſpect of his right of dominion over them, upon which account he is indued with the more peculiar image of God, which as a King is imprinted in him, and therein doth repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the perſon of God in his ſoveraignty, which the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of the people cannot pretend to, in relation they are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and that notion ſpeaketh an inferiority.</p>
            <p>And though ſubordinate Magiſtrates in a ſort repreſent Gods Perſon, yet it is not directly, they immediately repreſenting the Kings, as he doth Gods; ſo that the beſt of the people (who are Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates) or the Kings Vicegerents, as he onely is Gods, who is the ſum of all power, and the King is his Ray, and all inferiour Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates are but ſhadows of that ray of Divinity.</p>
            <p>The Phanatiques inſiſting on the pretended principles of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſafety, peace and liberty, have practiſed licentiouſneſs, war and ruine to the kingdom, and therefore they moſt confidently aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, that all Laws, Statutes, Ordinances, Covenants, Engagements, Promiſes, Proteſtations, all acknowledgements, Vows, and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and all manner of obligations and expreſſions hereof are one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly binding unto the publique ſafety, and not at all (as they will have it) to the perſons of the Governours, but with reference thereto.</p>
            <p>Pray be pleaſed ſtrictly to perpend theſe damnable Poſitions, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently contrived by the Romaniſts and lately diſtilled into the facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirits of this nation, to teach us firſt to deſtroy our lawfull Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours by the plauſible pretences of new-modelled principles of Common Reaſon, juſtice and equity, have almoſt nulled all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Government, according to the ancient fundamental common and Civil laws, at laſt to make us a <hi>raſa tabula,</hi> if not ſomewhat worſe, that we might be forced to deem it more rational to have their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, (a bad one) rather then none at all imprinted in us.</p>
            <p>This plot is much more ſubtile then that of <hi>Gun-powder Treaſon,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:49016:8"/>when the old Jeſuits, or the new Quakers, by the under-hand inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations of Religion, peace and liberty have put the Phanatiques on the moſt horrid contrivances immaginable, and by a blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous impulſe of ſpirit, did adviſe them to juſtifie many extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſtrange and very illegall actions, as taking up arms, raiſing and forming Armies againſt the King, fighting againſt his perſon, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoning, impeaching, arraigning, trying and executing him, cutting off his head, baniſhing his children, aboliſhing Biſhops, Deans and Chapters, took away Kingly Government and the Houſe of Lords, brok the Crowns, ſold the Jewels, Plate, Goods, Houſes and Lands belonging to the Kings of this Nation, erected extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Courts of juſtice, and therein impeached, arraigned, and condemned his Majeſties moſt loyall ſubjects, Perſons eminent for moral honeſty and great piety, as ſo many notorious enemies to the publick Peace of the kingdom, when the laws in being and the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Courts of juſtice could not reach them: theſe were unknown ſtrange practiſes in this nation, and not at all juſtifiable by any known Laws and Statutes.</p>
            <p>And now I have been bold to preſent you with a view of the groſs crimes of the late times, moſt humbly deſiring the honourable Houſes to concurre with the King in the conſtitution of ſuch wholeſome Laws (as a ſanctuary) to defend the nation from the like horrid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrations for the future, and to give an impreſſion and terror to others, not to dare to commit the like violations, upon the incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of penalties proportioned to their demerits:</p>
            <p>Now I offer to your moſt ſerious conſideration, in your moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired thoughts, how God out of a continued ſeries of juſtice hath pleaſed in theſe various ſcenes of his Providence to give to divers actors in thoſe late fatal tragedies a true ſight of their great Errors, in a grievous ſenſe of their high ſufferings. Firſt, a faction of the Hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in the beginning of their Seſſion connived at tumultuary commotions, aſſaulting the late Kings moſt ſacred Perſon, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>favour of that noble Hero the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> as a means, where they could not conquer by ſtrength of argument, to out-talk with cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of the multitude, pretending to ſatisfie their juſt importunities (which indeed were arrogant mutinies) concluded to judge him (whoſe powerfull wiſdom would have bounded their inſolence) by a new coined word &amp; law of accumulative treaſon; when it had ſerved their turn, they condemned the law with the perſon, and truly more guilty then him, leſt it ſhould riſe up in judgement againſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49016:8"/>them to make them exemplary for their injuſtice.</p>
            <p>Not long after theſe new Juſticiaries were ſecluded the Houſe by the minor part of it, by power of the Army, to make them ſenſible how by a force of the tumults they firſt ſentenced <hi>Strafford,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards by liſted tumults they themſelves were ejected by their fellow-members, who not long after having pulled down the Houſe of Lords, murdered the Lords Anointed, and baniſhed his royal rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ruined his loyal ſubjects, were twice ejected by <hi>Cromwell</hi> and the Army, to give them a reflection of their wicked actions, and ſpeak a check to their farther diſloyalty, oppreſſion and ambition.</p>
            <p>And now at laſt the late <hi>Juncto</hi> (whoſe being and baſe contrivances had been entombed in their own empty ſculls, had they not been hatched by the warmth of a military power) have well requited the army their former civilities in caſhiering them their commands, and paid them their long ſcore of Arrears with a ſhort empty vote of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity, which I hope will make them ſenſible of their groſs miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanours, in the juſt turn of their miſeries.</p>
            <p>And here I cannot but eternally give my thanks to that great God, who after ſo many ſtrange alterations of Governors and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, will make you inſtrumental in your ſage counſels, to make a perfect ſettlement in our diſtracted State and diſtreſſed Church.</p>
            <p>And this putteth me in mind of paying of my moſt humble gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to that moſt excellent Gen. <hi>Monke,</hi> who out of a great prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of honor, hath preſerved the ancient and famous City, (the Metropolis of the kingdom) from being made the prey of ſome <hi>Boutefeus</hi> of the late <hi>Juncto,</hi> who intended (as I am informed) had not they been prevented by the infinitte mercy and power of God, after they had pulld down the Gates, raſed the Walls, and impriſoned the moſt conſiderable perſons for Religion and loyalty in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Council, whom they would at laſt have executed at their own doores, and then burnt the Charter of the City, and diſarmed and plundred the moſt conſcientious Citizens, if they would not proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute the honour of their ſouls in a baſe compliance with them in the acknowledgement of the late barbarous <hi>Juncto</hi> to be the ſupreme Authority of the Nation.</p>
            <p>My moſt humble deſires unto your Excellency are, that as you have been already pleaſed in a handſome act of clemency to open the doores to the ſecluded members, you will adde a further obligation of your juſtice in protecting the two honourable Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the further violence of the Phanatiques, who by open
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49016:9"/>force have diſſolved many Parliaments, contrary to the known Laws; in which they have rendred the Nation ſinful to God, ſhameful to themſelves, and a ſcorn to the world.</p>
            <p>Into your hands it is put by divine providence to ſtop the rage and ambition of the Anapaptiſts, highly acted with pernicious prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Jeſuits, who at this time deſign in the diſſolution of this Parliament a total ſubverſion of the true Reformed Religion, and our ancient and well-eſtabliſhed civil government, and cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to introduce, under the notion of new lights, the old darkneſs of Roman Error and ſuperſtition, and under fair pretences of liberty and common ſafety in a Free State, to ruine and enſlave us to the power of forreign Princes.</p>
            <p>The onely way to render your ſelves high in the eſteem of the world, is to make your ſelves a full Parliament, conſiſting of the three eſtates of the kingdome; an excellent frame and compoſition of the three governments, ſo rightly balanced according to the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent inſtitution of it in a well-tempered Monarchy in the King, Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocracie in the Lords, and Democracie in the Commons; each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular intereſt complying ſo handſomely in a fair correſpondence with each other, the inferiour ſtill ſubſcribing to the ſuperiour in a regular ſubordination without animoſity or diſpute.</p>
            <p>So that this admirable conſtitution may be juſtly ſtyled Monarchy without Tyranny, Ariſtocracie without ambition, and Democracie without Anarchy; every man a freeholder concurring by his repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives to redreſs his grievances, and to conſtitute the Laws of the nation, to which he is in all juſtice obliged in a due obſervance moſt readily to ſubſcribe, when by his power in the adviſe of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legates they are enacted.</p>
            <p>And to that end in compleating the Parliament (he being head of it) you will give a great honour to your ſelves, happineſs to the nation, and glory to God, in being inſtrumental under him to bring in the King, a moſt glorious perſon, of Majeſtick aſpect, beautified with rare proportions of body, poliſhed in an excellent deportment, all ſubſervient to the more noble operations of his ſoul, commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating the choice notions of it in an elegant purity of ſpeech, his ſignificant expreſſions in great variety of languages, being ſo many different emblemes, that plainly interpret, and clearly comment upon the inward characters of his acute fancy, and profounder judgement.</p>
            <p>And his heroick habits of perſonal valour, juſtice, prudence, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49016:9"/>clemency, meekneſs, humility, temperance, faithfulneſs, conſtancy in his Religion, and above all his moſt eminent charity in forgiving his enemies, ſpeak him moſt illuſtrious, and highly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed in moral, intellectual, and Theological virtues; ſo that if he had no title to the Crown by right of inheritance (in its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent to him through ſo many Royal anceſtours) yet his incompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable merits would juſtly challenge your election of him to be your King.</p>
            <p>But if theſe ingenuous principles will not obliege you to your duty, pray be pleaſed to conſult the great nationall advantages. Our high born King, being allied to moſt if not to all the Princes of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, his Royal intereſt will make our peace with them, and give the banquerupt kingdom ſuch a repute with forreign Princes and Nations, that it will highly advance our decaied trade in tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our various manufactures, the great imployment and ſupport of the meaner ſort of the kingdom.</p>
            <p>You cannot give your ſelves a greater boon, nor the kingdom a grerter ſatisfaction, then to call in the King without ſigning ſuch conditions, which in effect will make him a Duke of <hi>Venice,</hi> it is not conſiſtent with the duty of Subjects to impoſe ſuch reſtrictions on their Soveraign, which ſhall render null in him, the ſacred function of ſupreme Magiſtracy, which is not of humane inſtitution, and therefore it cannot be reſumed with the hands of the people, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving an affront to God himſelf the true doner of it, and let thoſe look for the full viols of Gods wrath to be powred out upon them, in being given into the hands of a military power, for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of juſtice, as a due puniſhment for taking away the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia from the true owner, as of late we have been two ſenſible of, in impoſing ſuch articles in treating with the late moſt pious King, to which in honour and conſcience he could not conſent.</p>
            <p>I hope God will vouchſafe you more gracious tempers, then to diſpute the Kings moſt indubitate right, and Regal dignities, with which his Royal Aunceſtours have been formerly poſſeſſed: do not ſtudy to gratifie the puſillanimous fear of thoſe, who think they have ſo highly diſoblieged him in their unparalleled actions, that they have no ſecurity for their perſons and fortunes, except he be rendred incapable of deſerving them, in the loſs of his power, this is to puniſh him becauſe they have offended, and to keep him from doing civil juſtice to the nation, to protect their injuſtice from a due cenſure in the old current of the Law.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:49016:10"/>
            <p>Do not blaſt your own reputation, and thoſe great hopes the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom conceiveth of you, in not giving the King his ancient Rights, the Parliament its due priviledges, do not abridge the power of the Militia, and deem you do him right, in giving him an empty title, without power to vindicate it, which is no more, then to let him wear a fair ſcabbard, and take away his ſword.</p>
            <p>His late gracious Father choſe rather to quit his life, then that juſt power of the ſword, in which by divire Right, and his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance he was eſtated: now is the time to make ſatisfaction to his glorious ſon (as his immediate heir) for thoſe matchleſs violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which have been offered to his Fathers ſacred perſon; do not think to expiate the guilt of former times, (which long hath laid heavy on the nation) in ingaging in the ſame errors, with which they were juſtly branded.</p>
            <p>The Militia is that, which ſpeaketh him the chief Magiſtrate, which protecteth his ſacred perſon, and his ſubordinate magiſtrates in the exerciſe of juſtice, and in preſſing of the ſevere execution of thoſe penal laws upon malefactours, to the due loſs of their lives, liberties, and fortunes, to which (though never ſo juſt) they would not out of a partial love to themſelves ſubmit, unleſs compelled by a ſtronger coercive power.</p>
            <p>It is but a vain ſpeculation to ſtyle him ſupreme, and at the ſame time inveſt the people with the power of the ſword, who may (when they pleaſe) diſpute his commands (though never ſo lawfull) if they hold not a compliance with their deſires, having a deſign to abrogate or leſſen the juſt rights of the Crown, which though never ſo much according to the law of God and man, yet they may eaſily pretend as heretofore hath been done in the late <hi>Juncto</hi>) that they are tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and inconſiſtent with the liberty of the freeborn people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in that they give a check to thoſe incendiaries, who under the fair gloſſes of common ſafety, and liberty, have ſacrificed the King, and people, and all ſacred, moral, and national laws and liberties to their own baſe tyranny and avarice.</p>
            <p>Though for the preſent, for the breaches of priviledges of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the unlawful reſiſtance of Kingly power we have been late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whipped by the divine hand (inflicting great ſufferings on us as a due puniſhment for our greater ſins) into a thought of reſtoring the ſupreme Magiſtrate, to whom (as Gods Vicegerent) we truly intend to pay a juſt duty of Allegiance.</p>
            <p>Yet ſucceeding ages being not ſenſible of our ſmarts and ills, may
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49016:10"/>be ſo dandled with the ſame vain phantaſies, the people (being natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally adorers of power and licentiouſneſs) ſhould, being led by their forefathers example (whom they may count honourable to imitate) when before prepoſſeſſed with their own ambitious deſires, may by our fault fall into our errors and miſeries, if the King being diſar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the loſs of his Militia, ſhall not be able to defend himſelf and his loyal ſubjects, againſt the inſolence of his rebellious oppreſſors.</p>
            <p>Be not pleaſed to entertain your ſelves with the leaſt ſuſpicion, that the King will not weild the ſword of juſtice (in the moſt pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and pious Managery of his government over us) with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt moderation and integrity imaginable: be pleaſed ſeriouſly to conſider in his low ebbe of condition, being expoſed to the charity of forreigners, how obnoxious he was rendered to a ſea of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, when he was highly imbarqued among them, courting him with a powerfull aſſiſtance in order to the reſtauration of his Royall dignities, if he would innovate his Religion, chooſing rather to dure the worſt of fortune then by a forreign invaſion to gain a Crown in the forfeiture of his honour, conſcience and religion.</p>
            <p>What can be more pleaſing to God, and advantageous to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then honourably to poſſeſs the King with his own, without ugly obligations, which will reaſonably induce him (he being ſo much a friend to himſelf, to improve his utmoſt endeavours to free himſelf from thoſe bonds, which ſhall be unjuſtly impoſed upon him, and this will create ſuch a perpetual jealouſie between him and his people, that it muſt neceſſarily ſpeak them both mutually un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy.</p>
            <p>But the great Remora and obſtruction of the Kings Royal and free inauguration in order to civils, is the oppoſition of thoſe, who have poſſeſſed themſelves of the Crown, Biſhops, Dean and Chapter Lands and Revenues, in anſwer to which the King out of his graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous condeſcenſion to a firm peace, will vouchſafe not to be his own carver, wholly refering himſelf to the Honourable Houſes, who will aſſuredly treat them with all the juſtice and equity imaginable.</p>
            <p>And for his own part, let them read for their ample ſatisfaction his late Declaration, wherein he promiſeth they ſhall have his lands and the Churches till they are reimburſed of the money, principal and intereſt, which they have paid for them, and they are bound in conſcience to reſtore them to the true owners, the Church and Crown.</p>
            <p>In order to Eccleſiaſticks, the onely way to make up the ſad breaches
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49016:11"/>of the Church in point of doctrine and diſcipline, is to reſtore the ancient and Reverend Fathers of it, inſtituted by the holy Apoſtles (as conſervatours of it) againſt hereſie and ſchiſme; and our graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soveraign when he ſhall be intruſted with the government, out of his Princely care and Royal inclinations will preſerve the unity of of the Church, that nothing ſhall be impoſed on truly conſcienci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons contrary to their different judgements, profeſſing the ſame fundamentals of Orthodox Chriſtian Religion, and differing onely in circumſtancials, conditionally they deport themſelves with humility not intrenching on the publick in giving a diſturbance to the unity of the Church and peace of the nation.</p>
            <p>Nothing can give me a greater truth and admiration, then by ſad experience to ſee <hi>England,</hi> moſt eminent heretofore for Religion and Loyalty, ſhould in this preſent age ſo far degenerate from the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of our Church, and the ancient honour of the nation, who have had ſo high a duty for their native Prince that they had rather quit thier lives, then their ſenſe of Allegiance.</p>
            <p>Wherefore my moſt humble requeſt to the two honourable Houſes our faithful Truſtees is, that they would be pleaſed to repair the honour of the nation (ſo loſt abroad that no traveller dareth own himſelf an Engliſh man, being in danger of being ſacrificed, except he recant the publick errors of the nation) in the moſt honourable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of the King, moſt Illuſtrious in vertue and Religion, Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his juſt Rights by law, and vindicate the ancient privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Parliament, and the due liberty and propriety of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, which will ſpeak glory to God, and honour to your ſelves and the Nation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49016:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
